<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The secretary in fashion: or, A compendious and refined way of expression in all manner of letters. Composed in French by P. Sr de la Serre, historiographer of France. And translated into English, by John Massinger, Gent</title>
            <title>Secrétaire à la mode. English</title>
            <author>La Serre, M. de (Jean-Puget), ca. 1600-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115331</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850550</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850550</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 971:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The secretary in fashion: or, A compendious and refined way of expression in all manner of letters. Composed in French by P. Sr de la Serre, historiographer of France. And translated into English, by John Massinger, Gent</title>
                  <title>Secrétaire à la mode. English</title>
                  <author>La Serre, M. de (Jean-Puget), ca. 1600-1665.</author>
                  <author>Massinger, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 48 p., 49-56, a-d leaves, 57-131, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J[ohn] B[eale] and S[tephen] B[ulkley] for Godfrey Emerson, and are to be sold at his shop in Little Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Le secrétaire à la mode.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Letter writing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Secretary in Faſhion <hi>OR,</hi> A Compendious and Refined way of Expreſſion in all manner of LETTERS. <hi>COMPOSED IN FRENCH</hi> By P. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> de la SERR. Hiſtoriographer of FRANCE And Tranſlated into Engliſh, by JOHN MASSIN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ER, Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. B.</hi> and <hi>S. B.</hi> for <hi>Godfrey Emerſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Little Brittain.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORTHILY Admired for Learning and Good Parts, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Tho: Berney,</hi> Gent. of <hi>Grays-Inn.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought my endeavours too poorly imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, while they were reſtrain'd to the limits of a particular acknowledgement; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> forced me to comply with my ambitious humour, by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this publick profesſion of my duty &amp; obſervance. I may ſeem both Ignorant and Indiſcreet to
<pb facs="tcp:15760:3"/>
promiſe any new thing in this fardell of Epiſtles to you, vvho are able to give leſſons of Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Civility to the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Spirits of this age, yet I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve pardon, if you conſider that nothing is here but vvhat might either have bin written by you, or to you, and conſequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the approbation of the moſt malitious. For in the one your own Humanity, and in the other the Judgement of all the world is intereſſed: as is in all things that concerne your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, the repoſe,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant</hi> J. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:3"/>
            <head>TO MY LORD, THE Abbot of Dorak, one of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Privie Counſellors, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of the Holy Chappell at Paris.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Particular eſteeme I have of your Merit, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me to theſe Publick Proofes; being Ambitious the world ſhould know, that though my inclinations be not ſtrong enough to follow vertue, yet I never ceaſe to build her Altars, in al places where I find her Image. To maintain (my Lord) that you are one of the moſt lively, the Eloquence of your actions ſurpaſsing that of my Diſcourſe, has
<pb facs="tcp:15760:4"/>
already perſwaded it to al the world, ſo that your Honeſty having made it ſelfe known every where, I ſatisfie my ſelfe in praiſing you worthily, to declare your name, being one of the moſt accompliſhed Prelates of this Age. I ſpeake not of thoſe negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Importance which you have finiſhed, to the Honour of the King, and Satisfaction of his Emminence who knew right well that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Employments were under the reach of your Capacity. I wiſh with Paſsion, I had any in your ſervice, wherby I might force you to beleeve that I am extreamly</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble, and moſt faithfull ſervant,</hi> P. de La. Serre.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:4"/>
            <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving had notice given mee, that my <hi>Secretary of the Court,</hi> which I compoſed for a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement in my Youth, ran through the World in my Name, and with ſome kind of Approbation in ſtrange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: as being 30 times Printed, ſince it was firſt publiſhed, and never falling into my hands to be corrected: I thought good to preſent thee with this new one, which is a Digeſted worke, and where thou ſhalt receive more ſatisfaction, as finding a leſſe number of faults. It beares the Name of <hi>Secretary in Faſhion,</hi> to the end that it may be alwayes in ſeaſon, conſidering how va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable
<pb facs="tcp:15760:5"/>
the manner of Writing is. Receive it with as good a heart as I give it thee: and if it like thee not, learne charitably to hold thy Tongue, or elſe to reproach with a good grace; tis the beſt counſell I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to give thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here preſent thee with a <hi>Cornu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copia</hi> of knowledge and Expreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If thou doſt not receive it with an acknowledgement proportioned to the Worth of ſuch a Gift, mayſt thou acquire two <hi>Cornucopia's</hi> of Ignominy, to Adorne thy forehead, and bee condemned to the Reading of the <hi>Engliſh Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary,</hi> as long as thou liveſt. If the whole Mountaine of the Common-wealth (whereof thy ſelfe art a molehill,) were as ſenſible as thou oughteſt to be, I aſſure my ſelfe, ſhee would bow her venerable knees, and doe mee Homage for that mighty Portion of Wit, and Courtſhippe, whereof ſhee goes now to take Poſſeſsion. But I ſee thee already blear-eyed with reading <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Balzaac,</hi> and the <hi>Packet of Letters;</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give mee good Reader, I aske thee moſt humbly Mercy, and with much Reſentment call backe my former Imprecation, ſince I perceive thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready expoſed to a more rigorous Pennance, than
<pb facs="tcp:15760:6"/>
that which my Charity would have ſuffered my Juſtice to impoſe upon thee: For what miſcheif could I have imagined (though I had beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with the Soule of <hi>Phalaris</hi> his inginer) equall to the Malice of this which thou haſt already incurred? in the one thou learneſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to ſpeake Baudy with a good Grace, in the other nothing but to blow a horne; Here thou ſuckeſt in the Principles of Atheiſme, there of Ignorance; Here thou art inſtructed to Preach in an Epiſtle, there to Court thy Friend in a Sermon: This ſtuffs thy Memory with Stolne French, that with Engliſh not worth the Stea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: The one Commands thee to Violate the Laws of all Ancient Rhetorique, the other to obſerve none. The one will give thee Rules how to ſpeak <hi>Balzaac,</hi> (or) badly, the other like a Poſt <hi>(id eſt)</hi> nothing at all.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration of this (Loving, Kind, Courteous Reader) did much precipitate my Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Times from Error; or (as the Pure Hees and Shees of this Age ſay,) did even force my Spirit to reclaime the Idolatrous from adoring that Malicious Idoll the <hi>Engliſh Secretary,</hi> that Image which <hi>Nebuchadnezzar the King had ſet up, the Poſt</hi> with a <hi>Packet of Letters,</hi> and that moſt abhominable <hi>Baal, Balzaac:</hi> by divulging this Peece of Excellent Workmanſhip, (which the Gods themſelves did hammer and frame in the Head of <hi>Monſieur La Serre;</hi>) by letting this Bird of Paradiſe
<pb facs="tcp:15760:6"/>
fly out of her Cage, that ſhe might recreate Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with the Charms of her Voyce, and reſuſcitate the Intombed Spirits of Men, from that Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſleep which the former <hi>Tarantulaes</hi> had throwne them into. Or as with moſt reaſon I may averre, by Publiſhing this new Ephimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to the World, which ſhall teach thee to know the Conjunctions of the Planets, or erring Stars; I meane the Connection of Wandring words and ſentences, uſed, and abuſed by Men of all ſorts <hi>ad Libitum.</hi> It will teach thee the riſing and ſetting of the Sun, or Elevation and depreſsion of Periods; The Ecclipſes in writing, as to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh amongſt ſounds, and to know when one obſcures another, or at leaſt renders it leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable. But if thou beeſt not yet Contented with this moderate touch of knowledge, it ſhall proceed farther, and open to thee a ſluſe of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſublunary Sciences whatſoever. Where canſt thou have better Philoſophy than here, where it teacheth thee how the rude Matter of an Epiſtle is to be informed with the ſpritefull Vivacity of Phraſes, and Apt Coherence of Periods? Where wilt thou prove an Arithmetitian, if not here, where thou art taught, that if thou add, or ſubtract but one word from the whole Number of an Epiſtle, thy Computation will prove falſe, and it utterly loſe the Grace and Sweetneſſe due unto it? If thou wouldſt be inſtructed in the Tacticks, where wilt thou learne a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act way of ordering Men and diſpoſing a Battle
<pb facs="tcp:15760:7"/>
than here, where one diſplaced, puts all the reſt out of order? Humanity cannot invent a more compendious way of Short writing, ſince Steno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy has here arrived to ſuch Perfection, that when a Man has but writ his Name, hee has both Courted his Miſtreſſe, Comforted the Sick, Defied an Enemy, and Obliged a Friend. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick I am ſure, is here in her <hi>Auge,</hi> ſince our Syllogiſmes are ſo powerfull, that except a Man would confeſſe himſelfe rude, and unreaſonable, (and conſequently no Man) he can never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Argument. What Rhetorick is more pleaſing than this, where ſervants and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are acquired in every page? What Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick more Harmonious than where we are ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous in teaching the true art of ſtopps, that when one only is eſcaped, the whole Aire is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Diſcord? I muſt confeſſe, our Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is an Antipode to Lilly (though Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more Compleat,) for wee doe not decline Words, but only Obſolecies, and Barbariſmes: nor have wee more than two Conjugations, <hi>viz.</hi> to doe you ſervice, and to revenge my ſelfe; by which we Conjugate all our other Verbs and Nouns be they what they will.</p>
            <p>Behold Reader, beyond thy Expectation, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Ars magna et Ultima,</hi> beſides the Lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian; another Panace or Curer of all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes beſide the Graecian; and another Caſtle of Knowledge beſide Records Sphere; which if thou accept with a Willing mind, and good
<pb facs="tcp:15760:7"/>
Intention, Ile deifie thee; but if thou attempt upon it with unwaſhed hands, or a Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Opinion, I defie thee; and ſo fare thee well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant, <hi>J. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15760:8"/>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>THE FIRST LETTERS OF COMPLEMENT.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Take ſuch delight in rendring you my ſervice, that I remaine alwayes the firſt ſatisfied though I acquit my ſelfe And that which makes mee ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in ſeeking Occaſions, is, that you ſhould not reproach me to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any. Yet in this Sir I doe not implor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your beleife, deſiring ſo to let you ſee by Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, rather then Words, that I am without Complement,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15760:9"/>
               <head>Another upon the ſame Subject.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Defie you to accuſe me of neglect in the performance of my Duty, the paſſion which I have to your Service being ſo violent, that it nouriſheth in mee a continuall Care of ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Opportunities to make it knowne. To the furtherance of which, this Letter offerd it ſelfe moſt happily, having charge to aſſure you from my part, that of all the ſervants which your Merits have acquired you, I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>The moſt humble and moſt faithfull.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am by ſo many obligations Yours, that the onely want of Occaſions to give Teſtimony of it, breeds all my Diſcontents. Eſteeming my ſelfe unfortunate in nothing ſo much, as that the Paſſion which carries me to your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, prooves as unprofitable as extreame. Which forceth me to have recourſe to Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, beſeeching you to honour me with your Commands, that (other meanes failing) my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience may oblige you to believe that I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15760:9"/>
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Muſt diſcharge my heart in telling you that I honour you more then all the reſt of the World. Tis true your deſert impoſed the neceſſity upon me, but it did not give me the inclination: though I beſeech you to beleeve that I was very willing in the conſtraint, having ſuffer'd no other violence, then what my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Iudgement offer'd mee. You ſhall have daily new proofes by the Continuation of my Duty, and by the Quality which I beare</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame ſubiect.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you expect nothing but Complements from me, you ſhall never receive any, I am a Sworne enemy of Courtſhip and Civility towards perſons whom I honour extreamely, as I doe you. It ſufficing mee that I performe my Duty in their behalfe, and that I take care to do it with a good Grace. This is the Study in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15760:10"/>
which I practice my ſelfe, and I beſeech you thinke that I will not looſe the leaſt occaſion to witneſſe it to you, becauſe I finde my ſelfe much intereſſed in the Reſolution which I have taken, to be all my life</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THough I have told you a thouſand times by word of Mouth that I am your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, yet my Pen ſhall once aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, expecting till you oblige me, to more Eminent proofes; which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure you do to, &amp; (if you be pleaſed) to prevent the occaſion by ſome Command, that may ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my Impatience, to make you know and confeſſe at the ſame time, that you may have more powerfull, and more conſiderable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, but never</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>A more humble, or more faithfull.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15760:10"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters of Complement.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Never made doubt of your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility and Courteſie, but of my owne good fortune, in meeting with the meanes to require them. Yet I intreat you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that hereafter I will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all my cares to witneſſe unto you my good affection, and if Ill meanes render them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, I will dye for my owne ſatisfaction,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your very humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Eſteeme to much the Honour of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, not to deſire the continuation, and withall to beſeech you for ſome Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, wherein I may witneſſe the Paſſion which I have to your ſervice. For which I will importune you hereafter, deſiring by deeds
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15760:11"/>
rather then words to let you ſee, that I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt affectionate ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THough this in ſome ſort requite the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of your remembrance, yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ceaſe to be indebted to you, when I conſider, that your courteſie prevented my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; But I beſeech you imagine, that for the Time to come, I will bee ſo carefull to diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my ſelfe, that you ſhall have greater cauſe to complaine of my importunity, then my ſilence: which I have reſolved never to keepe, when your Intereſts oblige me to the contrary, as making Publike Profeſſion to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in all places</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Will be ſo preſumptuous (ſince you deſire it) as to beleeve you love me; but upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15760:11"/>
that you will likewiſe acknowledge the Paſſion, which I have to ſerve you. For as it onely makes mee merit the honour of your Friendſhip, ſo I ſhall be very glad, that you would everlaſtingly conſerve the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of it. Continue then in loving mee as much as you pleaſe, and likewiſe eſteeme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly that I am, more then all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THough I give you very humble thanks for the Honour of your Remembrance, yet I ſhall alwayes remaine Indebted to you, as making more account of the leaſt of your favours, then all the reſpects I am able to render you. Continue onely in obliging mee of that faſhion (though I be intirely yours al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready) and beleeve (if you pleaſe) that I ſhall never bee capable of other reſentment, then which ſhall witneſſe the quality that I beare</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15760:12"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am not ſo unfortunate as I thought I was, ſince I hold ſome place ſtill in your Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Yet the Griefe which I have, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this honour, has reduced my thoughts, to ſuch a Moderation, that I am in doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhould complaine or rejoyce I r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>maines in you onely to allay the diſcontent of my Minde, by giving mee ſome Employment in your ſervice, which may witneſſe the Paſſion I have to maintaine the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your very humble Servant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters to complaine of a Long Silence.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Friendſhip and Service which heretofore I vowed you, force me at this preſent, to demand the Reaſon of your Silence. I doe not doubt but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15760:12"/>
alledge a ſufficient excuſe to authorize it, yet I beſeech you thinke, that how lawfull ſoever it bee, I ſhall never leave off Complaining: you may pretend the want of Occaſions, or the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Accident of ſome Sickneſſe, (which never moleſted you except in thought) whereby to Iuſtifie your ſelfe againſt my Reproaches. But all this is not able to ſatisfie mee, confeſſe your fault; aske forgiveneſſe, and you goe a nearer way to work, that's the onely way to conſerve eternally,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your very humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Shall breake with you at laſt, if you breake not ſilence, imagining that you love me but a little, ſince you have forgot me altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I beſeech you deale more familiarly with me, if my friendſhip be any way conſiderable, or you eſteeme mee worthy of yours. In the Humour I am now, I thinke you can no ſooner blot me out of your Memory, then I can raze you out of my heart, without retaining any thing (by my good will) but the Quality only,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15760:13"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you have taken an oath to write no more to me, at leaſt ſend mee the letters backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine which I addreſſed to you, that I may ſtill have the honour to receive ſomething from your part. Silence is a ſworne enemy of Friendſhip, which is the reaſon that mine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches you at this preſent, being not able to indure, that after ſo many proteſtations never to forget me, you ſhould looſe even the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of having made them. You may change your Humour when you pleaſe, if you deſire to renew the obligations</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble Servant,</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF I did not honour you extreamely, I could eaſily revenge my ſelfe of your forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by my ſilence; but the eſteeme which I make of your deſerts, together with an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which carries me to your ſervice, oblige
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15760:13"/>
me to aſſure you ſtill, that though you ſhould forget me, even to my name, I would never change the Reſolution which I have taken, to be all my life</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Can endure no longer that you ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a Perſon who honours you ſo extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as I doe. Theſe three Months of your ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence I have kept my minde in the continuall fetters of grief, that I ſhould looſe the honour of your Remembrance; I beſeech you doe me Juſtice, and let not all the World complaine with me, of the little eſteeme you make</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble Servant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>DOe if you pleaſe, write no more to mee, your merit conſtraines mee to uſe you in another faſhion. I can never weary
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15760:14"/>
my ſelfe, in executing your Commands, and leſſe in acquitting my ſelfe when Occaſions are offer'd, yet I doe not deſire that you ſhould eſteeme your ſelfe obliged to mee, for I ſatisfie my ſelfe alwayes the firſt, following my incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation after I have honoured your vertue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe equally both the one and the other force me to carry, to my Grave, the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble Servant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to the Letter Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Silence.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou oblige mee with ſuch a good Grace, in Complaining of mee, that I am conſtrained to give you thankes inſtead of reproaches. 'Tis not becauſe I want lawfull excuſes to authorize my Silence. But the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt which you take in it, makes mee to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne it, aſſuring you, that hereafter you ſhall accuſe me of Importunity rather then neglect. 'Tis the Proteſtation</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15760:14"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT is not needfull to excuſe my ſilence, ſince I ſtill indure the Paine of it; by reaſon of a Sickneſſe, which moleſts me continually. But though your Reproaches proceed from your Affection, yet I aſſure you they Intereſſe mine extreamely, being you doubt of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of it. I beſeech you thinke, that I am not of an humour to forget thoſe whom I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as I doe you, and that except I bee againe reduced to the extremity I was in before, I ſhall alwayes acquit my ſelfe of that which I owe you, In Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF our reciprocall friendſhip could not bee conſerved but by letters, my hand ſhould bee alwayes upon the Paper, to give you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15760:15"/>
continually ſome new aſſurance or other; But knowing that ſhe ſubſiſts of herſelfe, through her own ſolidity, I contemne all the Paintings of Civility and Complement. How little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſoever you have of your owne Deſert, or my Humour, you may eaſily know without being a Prophet the deare eſteeme I make of you, and being knowledge has truth for her object, you are forced to beleeve that I am really</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Complaints and Reproaches, are too agreeable to me, that I am forced to give you thanks, knowing they proceed from an exceſſe of affection, and zeale. 'Tis true I have beene ſilent too long, but I pray you beleeve, that the Misfortune which Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it upon me, hath given mee ſuch a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that I deſerve Pardon, though it were the moſt enormious crime of the World. I will not now make a particular recitall of all the Accidents which have befallen me, for feare you ſhould Iudge me as Importune in that, as in the other you eſteem'd mee negligent: It
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15760:15"/>
ſufficeth me to put you in minde, that I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, what I alwayes was,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU are too Iuſt to Condemne mee without hearing me ſpeake. Tis true I have beene ſomewhat too long in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitting, by the ordinary Commerce of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the debt which I owe you, but the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance of the Priſon where I am ſtill, can tell you, that though my hands bee free, yet their liberty is altogether unprofitable to ſerve them in that which you deſire. Content your ſelfe then (if you pleaſe) with the ſervices I am able to render you, that is, in good will and thought: without accounting this for one, ſince tis both by hazard &amp; an exceſſe of good Fortune, that I acquit my ſelfe of it. And beleeve aſſuredly, that into what extremity of adverſe fortune ſoever I am reduced, I will alwayes conſerve the paſſion I have to your Service, as being without Fiction</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15760:16"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Would I were leſt handed, that I might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit my ſelfe of the Service I owe you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unfortunately lame of the right hand: which has obliged me to make uſe of a ſtrange Penne, to excuſe my ſilence, and to aſſure you, that though I ſerve my ſelfe of another mans endeavour in writing this Letter, yet 'tis my ſoule that conceived it, and my heart that gave the Dictamen, being very glad to witneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the Truth of my thoughts, touching the Reſolution which I have taken to make my ſelfe remarqued in all places</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15760:16"/>
               <head>Letters of Thanksgiving.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince it is your pleaſure to adde dayly to the obligations of thoſe who are moſt intirely yours; I am reſolved to let you take your courſe, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy my thoughts onely in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king occaſions to revenge my ſelfe. And if my misfortune in this Purſuit continually render my cares unprofitable, yet for your ſatisfaction I ſhall alwayes have a good Will, and Paſſion to doe you Service, which I ſhall heartily of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you up being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Doe not intend that theſe thanks which I give you for the favour wherewith you were pleaſed to honour me, ſhould paſſe in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15760:17"/>
your opinion for an Acknowledgement: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge my ſelfe onely of your Civility, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting to meet with an occaſion, wherein I may witneſſe with Services rather then Words, that I am unfaignedly in heart, and ſoule</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your very humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Confeſſe you have obliged mee with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Grace, and ſo perfectly, that I ſhall remaine indebted to you all my life. I would to God ſome Occaſion would offer it ſelfe, which I might imploy in your Service, thereby to witneſſe, that as your favours have beene extreame, I will attempt all extreami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to revenge my ſelfe. Thoſe are no diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Complement, my heart dictates to my Penne, all that my Penne writes to you, with aſſurance that I will not long unprofitably beare the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your very humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15760:17"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Know not in what Tearmes, to give you Thanks, for the Favours which your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diſpoſition has beene pleaſed to be ſtow upon mee. I am ſo unfortunate an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, that I am out of all hope to acquit my ſelfe, that way. It ſufficeth me, to put you in minde of the Paſſion which I have to your Service, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading my ſelfe, that the remembrance it will excitate in you ſhall ſupplicate for the default of my Capacity, and that Conſidering the Ardor of my Zeale, rather then the beauty of my Diſcourſe, you will content your ſelfe with my Disability, and that I aſſure you once againe, how perfectly I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your very humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF I had beene more happy or more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, I had already requited your favours inſtead of giving you thanks; but being unfortunate as I am, and in ſuch a degree of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15760:18"/>
Impotency, I have nothing left but words, to ſend you, as an acknowledgement of your Deeds. Tis true, they are words moſt infallibly true, aſſuring you from my heart rather then my mouth, that I will carry to my Grave, the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you expect Thanks worthy your favours, you ſhall never receive any of me. I am farre more fit to publiſh them, then requite them in the leaſt reſpect, if the good deſire I have to diſingage my ſelfe, doe not paſſe for ſatisfaction: which is all that I can offer you in the ſtate I finde my ſelfe at this preſent, beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching you to beleeve, that if I were not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with an extreame Misfortune, my Care and Paines ſhould ſoone witneſſe the Occaſion which is offered me, to give Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony how much I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15760:18"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters of Thanksgiving.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our thankes have bought my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice at ſo deare a rate, that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which before I received is utterly now taken from me. Keep your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omplements then for ſome other, and remember to uſe more familiarly,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>The moſt humble of all your ſervants.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THere is farre more Honour, then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in ſerving you, ſince by ſuch ready acknowledgements, you haſten the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. The exceſſe of your Nobleneſſe, undoes me, not being able to endure thanks for the performance of my duty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince my indeavours in your behalfe can bee ſtiled no other, I beſeech you to vary
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15760:19"/>
your Tearmes, and to Conſider me alwayes in the Quality I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant,</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Complaine much of the Exceſſe of your Civility and Courtſhip, ſince our Recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call friendſhip is therein greatly Intereſſed. you give me Thanks for the ſervice which you deſired of mee, as though I were not obliged to it of Neceſſity. Leave off that ill Cuſtome if you Pleaſe, and know that the Language of Complements is unknowne to true friends, whereof I am one, and which is more,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15760:19"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Complements have put me into a very ill humour; I cannot write to you, but in Choller, ſince you uſe mee as a ſtranger, like as app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ares by the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity of your Ceremonies and unprofitable Thanks. It ſeemes you have wholly forgot the abſolute power that your Merit has obtain'd over me, which cauſes mee once againe to put you in minde, that you will be ſooner weary in Commanding, then I in executing, as being unreſervedly,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Send you backe your Thanks, to the End that you may make uſe of them, when you entertaine ſome perſon leſſe endeared to your ſervice then I am. One would thinke by reading your complements, that you Cog with me to gaine my Friendſhip. I pray Remember Sir, that I have wholly dedicated it to your
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15760:20"/>
deſert, and therefore, you are obliged hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to treat mee with leſſe Civility, and more freedome, if you account mee into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your Servants, I being,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>One of your moſt humble, and moſt faithfull</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur thanks have made mee reſolve to doe that piece of Service over againe, Imagining that ſomething was omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſince you goe about to put mee in minde of it, by your unneceſſary Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment. Sir you know that kinde of affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is alwayes ill received in the familiar Commerce, of a true friendſhip, which I ſhall alwayes profeſſe in your behalfe, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15760:20"/>
               <head>Letters of Intreaty.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Report of your generous Diſpoſition gives me the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to implore your favour in the diſpatch of a buſineſſe, whoſe ſucceſſe depends abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely on your Authority. Tis true I have not the Honour to bee knowne by you, but that being a particular Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fortune of Mine, I deſire it may not ſerve as a pretence to the Refuſall of my Demand: Aſſuring you, that I ſhall indeavour to make knowne by re-all ſervice, rather then name,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Could wiſh your Command had preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my Intreaties, that my obſervance might have merited of you the diſpatch
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15760:21"/>
of a buſineſſe which preſents it ſelfe. But being the occaſion to Importune you, was offer'd, when I ſought one to doe you ſervice, I will force my ſelfe to beleeve that my good will may oblige you, not to refuſe this courteſie</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>to <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY vowed Service and Friendſhip, give mee the freedome to Implore your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, in behalfe of the Bearer of theſe Preſents, I ſerve my ſelfe very boldly of the Power you have given me to imploy your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors in all ſorts of encounters, but upon Condition that you will doe the ſame in all occaſions that may offer themſelves, wherein I may witneſſe how much I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:15760:21"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you make as great Account of my Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as I doe of your commands, you will eaſily accord unto me this, which is, to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine with your Authority, a buſineſſe of Mine now in agitation, that it may bee deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to my advantage. I doe not doubt of your Power, and leſſe of your Nobleneſſe, which forces me to beleeve that you will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with this Occaſion offerd you, to oblige extreamely,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you complaine of my Importunity, accuſe your owne freeneſſe, for if you had beene leſſe Generous, I had bin leſſe bold. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I know by Experience in what a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree Civility &amp; Courteſie predominate in you, I am conſtrain'd to think, that my intreaty will not be inacceptable, which is, that you would
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15760:22"/>
bee pleaſed to mollifie with your Eloquence, that harſh conceipt that Maſter N. has of mee. In this incounter you will oblige us both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſince giving him to underſtand my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, hee will eaſily give place to reaſon. This favour in particular I hope from your Goodneſſe, as you on the contrary may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect all ſorts of Service from my Duty: In Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi> M</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THough I bee the moſt unprofitable of all your friends, yet I ſhall never faile to prove my ſelfe one of the moſt paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to your Service. The violence whereof cauſes me at this Preſent, to intreate you to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me in ſuch, or ſuch an Encounter. All that I can ſay to you for the firſt acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, that I ſhall conſerve Eternally the Memory of this favour, and if I be not able to meet with an Occaſion to revenge my ſelfe,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15760:22"/>
that I ſhall carry the Sorrow of it into my Grave, together with the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters of Intreaty.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have done all that you deſired of me, but with ſo much ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and ſo little Paines, that I beſeech you prepare ſome new commands, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the paſſion I have to ſerve you, may not be left unprofitable, and you ſhall ſee by my obſervance, that I have no greater Pleaſure in the World, then to make my ſelfe remarqued in all places,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15760:23"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have many thankes to returne you for the happy imployment you gave mee in your ſervice; I thinke all things fell out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your deſire, which gave mee ample occaſion to rejoyce, as participating in all things that concerne your particular. I beſeech you doe me the favour, that I may never have occaſion to doubt of it, ſince I profeſſe my ſelfe as much as any man in the World,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Could wiſh you had every day occaſion to command my ſervice, that I might conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually have the Good fortune to produce new proofes of my obedience. I perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med happily the laſt Commands wherewith you were pleaſed to honour mee, which gives me cauſe to believe that you will not long let me reſt unprofitable, without giving me ſome other ſort of imployment, wherein I may finde
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15760:23"/>
more ſatisfaction, as prooving it more paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. This I beſeech you to doe, in quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble Servant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Finde ſo much facility in the execution of the Command, which you impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee, that I am aſhamed to reckon it in the number of ſervices which I deſire to render you: It being an Encounter of ſo little Importance, for my ſatisfaction and your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, that I beſeech you give me ſome other Imployment, wherein I may witneſſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your Merit and my Affection how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faignedly I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15760:24"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Aske you pardon for the long time that I have ſpent in the executing your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, not that I have beene negligent in employing my Cares, and Diligence, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſucceſſe conſiſting in a Strangers power, I could no ſooner give you the Effects: yet let not the miſhap of this delay, hinder you hereafter in uſing my Endeavours, ſince I am without reſerve</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHen you deſire any ſervice of me, I beſeech you conſider whether it be in my power or no, to the end that being unable to execute your Commands (as I am at this Preſent) I incurre not the hazard of your reproach. You may Expect new proofe (when you pleaſe) of the Paſſion which I have to ſerve you, ſince I no way deſire to beare in vaine the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble Servant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15760:24"/>
               <head>Other Anſwers of Excuſe to the Letters of Intreaty.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am more ſorry then your ſelfe, that I am not able to effect your Commands: The duty which you expect, does not abſolutely depend of mee, ſo that to render it worthily, I am to implore the favour of an other Man, who profeſſeth to incline totally to the adverſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Doe not thinke that I make theſe excuſes to avoid the occaſion, which preſented it ſelfe for your ſervice, but beleeve I beſeech you, that in all other Encounters, I will Comport my ſelfe with ſo much paſſion, that you ſhall be forced to confeſſe I am unfaignedly,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15760:25"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you knew in what diſorder my Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune cauſes me to write, (ſince I am not able to ſatisfie your deſire) you would have pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on my Affliction, being it wholly proceeds from my Griefe, that the Power to doe you ſervice is taken from mee. I ſpeake this from my heart, and ſoule, and being the friendſhip I promiſed you taught mee the Language, I will conſtraine my ſelfe to beleeve, that it is Eloquent enough to perſwade you, that the only want of ability, deprives mee at this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, of the Honour and Contentment, to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto you how much I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15760:25"/>
               <head>Congratulatory Letters to a friend, of ſome Good Fortune happened to Him.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you knew how exceſſively joyfull I was at the Newes of your good fortune, you would make a doubt whether your owne reſentment might be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled to mine or no: truly Sir there could nothing be added to it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it proceeds wholly from the friendſhip that long agoe I vowed to your good nature, which is not vulgar, ſince it has your deſert for the Object. I could ſay more if the Exceſſe of my Gladneſſe would give me the freedome, wherefore for the Preſent I muſt ſuffice my ſelfe, that you remaine aſſured, how the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment which I take can be equalled by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the paſſion which I have to your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your very humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15760:26"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe newes of your Promotion into that Charg, which you wiſh'd for ſo long, have added ſuch Contentment and Satisfaction to my thoughts, that I am able to expreſſe but one part of the Ioy which raignes in me. I trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not my ſelfe, to perſwade you to it by a long diſcourſe; your owne merit and our reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall Friendſhip, (ſupplying the defect of my Eloquence) will give a farre better Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony then my pen is able, which has in charge at this preſent onely to put you in minde, that I am alwayes according to my wont</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe part which I alwayes tooke in your Intereſts, ſhall witneſſe unto you at this Preſent, the exceſſe of my joy which I conceived at the newes of your Good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: &amp; though I be not one of the firſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate it with you, yet I am one of the moſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15760:26"/>
ſenſible, in the common Contentment which poſſeſſeth the World. The diligence, or delay of a Poſt can advance, or diminiſh no mans duty in this kinde of encounter, ſince nothing but Zeale, and Affection are conſiderable, which gives mee great confidence at this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as being more then any man in the world,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>DOe not admire that I am one of the laſt, who congratulate with you, your good fortune: the joy which I conceived was ſo extreame, that it could afford mee no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Liberty to acquit my ſelfe. I know, the moſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your friends have prevented me, but being their ſatisfaction is ſmall, I doe not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if their diligence be the greater. As for my part my idleneſſe increaſeth my Merit, ſince the ſtay and Protraction proceeded only from the exceſſe of the Gladneſſe</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15760:27"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce you doubt not the Friendſhip which I have promiſed you, you will eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that I was extreame ſenſible of the Good fortune which happen'd you of late, but I muſt tell you, that as your merit made mee foreſee it in you long before it came, ſo I was not much aſtoniſhed at the firſt recitall. I wiſh you daily the like, or greater advancements, being unable to acquit my ſelfe otherwiſe then by prayers of the great debt I owe you. Yet how unfortunate or unprofitable ſoever I be, doe not ceaſe to continue me in the Number</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt obedient and faithfull ſervants,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu muſt imagine if you pleaſe, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment which the Newes of your Good Fortune imprinted in me, ſince I am not able to expreſſe it as it is in it ſelfe. But if in this you have neede of any ſuccour, your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15760:27"/>
may aſſiſt you by putting you in Minde, of the Paſſion which I have for your Service; 'tis that onely which cauſed the exceſſe of my Ioy, and to which you can adde nothing, but by honouring me with your Commands, ſince by that meanes my Obedience may give mee, the perfect Contentment of being able to teſtifie unto you how much I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, and moſt faithfull.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters of Congratulation.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Alwayes beleeved you were ſo Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, as to take part in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhould concerne me, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun ſo ſtrict a Commerce of Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall Friendſhip. And I perſwade my ſelfe likewiſe, that you make no doubt of the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I have to doe you ſervice (by which Meanes onely I am able to Merit the Effects of your Nobleneſſe.) Whereof you may bee as Confident, as of the moſt aſſured thing in the World, ſince I am in heart, and ſoule,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:15760:28"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce you take part in the good fortune which has befalne me, you muſt alſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate in the advantage of the new Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit which it has brought mee into. This I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe you of, to the End that you let not any occaſion ſlip, wherein you may procure new proofes of my Paſſion, nor forget this advice which I give you; ſince I ſhall dye of Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if I expect long, the opportunity to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto you, how deepely I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your Servant, and Friend, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am not to thank you for theſe new proofes of your Nobleneſſe which you have ſhown in my behalfe, becauſe they are actions ſo proper to your Nature, that without them you could not poſſibly live. I muſt give you praiſes then, inſtead of thanks, and account my ſelfe happy, that I ſerve as an object, to your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15760:28"/>
Inclinations, whereof I ſhould become Envious, but that they do not admit any hopes of Imitation: and therefore I reſerve admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only to contemplate them, in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble Servant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe new aſſurances w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> you have given me of your friendſhip in bearing part of my good fortune, have yeilded me much more ſatisfaction then my advancement it ſelf, as preferring the Happineſſe of your Affection before my owne particular; you have touched me ſo ſenſibly, in mingling my intereſts with your own, that I ſhall never looſe the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſo great a favour: wiſhing that ſome occaſion would offer it ſelfe whereby I might in ſome part merit it by the reality of my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, ſince I am, and will be, all my life,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your very humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:15760:29"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu ſeeme to take pleaſure in nothing elſe, but in giving me dayly new proofs of your friendſhip, as if I were able to conceive any doubt of it at all. I know that you could not be ſo noble as you are, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you tooke part in the Content which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, for the happy ſucceſſe, of my affaire. And beſides making Profeſſion to love mee, in that height as I honour you, I know there was neceſſity for your ſatisfaction, and that you ſhould bee extreamely ſenſible of the good fortune,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble Servant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Began not to day to bee indebted to you for the free Teſtimonies of your friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, having given me ſo many proofes, that the diſability to revenge my ſelfe, has made me aſhamed of the Remembrance. But ſince
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15760:29"/>
you partake of the joy which I receive for the gaining of my ſuit, I conjure you to ſerve your ſelfe without exception, of all the Advantages which I have got, if you would really have me beleeve, that you account me of the number of your beſt friends as well</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>as of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt faithfull ſervants.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Congratulatory Letters to a Perſon of Eminent Quality.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I bee one of the laſt in Congratulating with your Lordſhip the New governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the king has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon you; yet I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your Lordſhip, that no Man forewent mee in witneſſing the Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo publike a Ioy. And as this duty which I render you is valuable according to the greatneſſe of my Zeale, and not of my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, ſo I thought that though it came ſomething late, it would not be leſſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15760:30"/>
If I had had no other object but your Lordſhips good Fortune, I had prevented in this actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all that have now got the ſtart of me; but taking nothing into my Conſideration, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your Deſert &amp; my Inclination to your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, I gave way to my own deſires rather then Cuſtome, which is to make my ſelfe remarked every where in effect, rather than appearance,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Could not be ſilent in the Acclamations of ſuch an univerſall Gladneſſe, being forced to ioyne my voice, to other Mens, in Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing our Commune Contentment touching the <hi>Mareschalſhip</hi> of France, wherewith the King has beene graciouſly pleaſed to honour you; This Action of Iuſtice is ſo highly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by every Perſon, that your Enemies are conſtrained to condemne themſelves to an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting ſilence, being not able to open their Mouthes, but to their owne Confuſion. Live then happily with this part of Good fortune which your merit firſt made you aſpire to, and believe aſſuredly, that in the whole traine of your Excellencies ſervants, there ſhall be very few able to imitate me, in the reſolution which I have taken, to carry to my grave, the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble &amp; moſt obedient Servant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:15760:30"/>
               <head>Letters to a Perſon of Note, acknowledging ſome notable favour received.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe not render you this duty as thanks, for the favours which your Goodneſſe has beene pleaſed to heape upon me, ſince their exceſſe force me to a ſilence, as taking from me all meanes to revenge my ſelfe. It ſufficeth me you beleeve, that I will ſooner looſe my ſelfe, then the remembrance of your bounty. I know your Lordſhip ſatisfied your ſelfe firſt, every time you obliged me; but being I cannot doe ſo, what advantage ſoever I take, without ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring you ſome ſervice of conſideration, I humbly beſeech your Lordſhip to grant mee the Liberty to Importune you at all times to honour me with your Commands, to the End that by the Innocncy of my obſervance, you may be conſtraind to know, that if you bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely generous, I am no leſſe ſenſible, nor no leſſe,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt faithfull Servant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15760:31"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you expect thanks worthy of the Favours wherewith you have beene pleaſed to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour mee, I humbly beſeech your Lordſhip to afford mee the tearmes that I may repeat them after you for your ſatisfaction. I confeſſe boldly my incapacity to expreſſe unto your Lordſhip the reſentment which your obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cauſe in mee, as well as my diſabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in meeting with occaſions to acquit my ſelfe. But being Generous actions carry their owne recompenſe along with them, all that I can doe, is to put your Lordſhip continually in minde of your Nobleneſſe, and to publiſh it in all Corners of the World, together with the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obedient ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15760:31"/>
               <head>Letters to aske Pardon for a Fault Committed.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the confeſſion of my fault, can merit any Grace, I will expect it from your Bounty, not my Intention, becauſe it is Innocent. Tis true I have loſt your good Affection by reaſon of the Paſſage laſt night, but ſince I was ſurprized by an extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of Anger, (which would not ſuffer mee to conſider where I was) I leave the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my weakneſſe to you, having whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned it my ſelfe. You know that our firſt motions are ſo ſoveraigne in their violence, that in contempt of reaſon they will undergoe no lawes but their owne; who ſhould obtaine of you to conſider that in the fault which I have committed, there was more contributed by nature, then my own free will; ſo that I knew not how to avoid it, I know at leaſt how to repent my ſelfe, of which I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you moſt faithfully to the end, that my moſt humble intreaties for your pardon and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15760:32"/>
favour, may bee made more acceptable, and the rather becauſe they proceed,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>from <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have too great an opinion of your Piety to make doubt of the Pardon which I crave, for my fault committed laſt night, 'tis not that I feare the Innocence of my Intention is not able to juſtifie me, but becauſe I would ſet my Minde in quiet, as I have already my Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. This act of acknowledgement ſhould ſerve you for a ſatisfaction, as it does me for a Pennance: putting you in minde of the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which alwayes heretofore I have had to doe you ſervice, and of the Profeſſion which I have made, to beare in all places, the Quality,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:15760:32"/>
               <head>Letters Reproaching a friend for the Coldneſſe of his Affection.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I made not an extream ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your friendſhip, I would not have complain'd of your ſilence, nor that Coldneſſe which you ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at our laſt meeting. I ſpeake not this, becauſe I would force your Love: but I ſhould bee very glad you would acknowledge the Affection which I have vowed you, whereby you might bee obliged to doe me juſtice in honoring me with the like, yet I leave you the liberty to doe as you pleaſe, againſt my will, I ſay againſt my will, becauſe I have taken Oath, to live and dye</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:33"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am conſtrain'd to put you in minde of thoſe proteſtations of friendſhip which once you made mee, being I perceive that yours growes already weary of her won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Conſtancy. You ſeeme to have forgot at the ſame time, both the eſteeme which I make of your Deſert, and the Paſſion which I have to your ſervice. Sir you may change your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour when you pleaſe, if you would have me beleeve you are not fickle in your Promiſes, and that you know the Art to Conſerve eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, thoſe that Endeare themſelves the moſt to you, as I doe, In Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant,</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:15760:33"/>
               <head>Letters to complaine of Backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting Speeches.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is told mee that you maintain'd a Certaine diſcourſe to my diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, I beſeech you out of Charity repent your ſelfe in time, if you would not have mee conſtraine you to a more rigorous Pennance, I underſtand not Ieſting, if I begin it not my ſelfe, wherefore correct your Pleadings, or I will cauſe you to looſe both your ſuit and charges. I give you this faire war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that you may have leſſe cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine hereafter, and when I ſhall perceive you in as humble a ſubmiſſion as I expect, Ile then take it into my conſideration whether I ought to be for the time to come, as hitherto I have beene</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:34"/>
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Underſtand that when you have nothing elſe to doe, you take upon you to backbite, a Perſon very neare allied unto mee. 'Tis the worſt trade and moſt dangerous that you can imploy your ſelfe in: but if your wine bee the cauſe of theſe extravagancies, I adviſe you to mingle it with water aſſoone as you can, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I ſhall bee conſtrain'd to force you to ſuch a long ſilence, that no man ſhall ever heare you ſpeake hereafter. 'Tis the Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble adviſe, if you follow it,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15760:34"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters of Complaint.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe not write this letter to give you ſatisfaction, but to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with my owne Humour, in the Innocence I have alwayes lived; you are too blame to make thoſe falſe reporters, my Iudges, from whoſe ſentence I appeale as from an abuſe, yet you may beleeve what you pleaſe, being you are unwilling to explicate your ſelfe any further. And if you be not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the Aſſurance I give, that I never dream'd of offending you, I leave you to faire Paper and Inke, wherby you may ſignifie unto me your minde, and Intention, whether good or bad I care not. It ſufficeth me, that you call to remembrance the Name and Quality which I once bore</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:35"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THoſe that told you I abuſed your kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman abuſe me, I know (without any Mans Intimation) the reſpect I owe to that ſex: and what ſubject ſoever ſhe had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, my reaſon ſhould alwayes have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me to hold my Peace. As for the reſt, know that wine never made me ſpeake, and if you be ſo fooliſh as to beleeve it, I know a way to puniſh your folly, I tell you what I meane to doe, that you may have no pretence to ſay I ſurprize you unawares, at our next meeting, where I have good hope to make you feele how worthily I can Chaſtize, thoſe that will not bee contented with reaſon, 'Tis the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your ſervant as much as you pleaſe.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:15760:35"/>
               <head>Letters to Iuſtifie ones ſelfe of a Reproach.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wonder greatly at the injuſtice you have done mee, being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſo reaſonable as you are: you have condemned me upon the firſt report of my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, without obſerving any other Formality then what your paſſion ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted. I muſt tell you, you appeare ſomething too violent in this Encounter, and the more, becauſe you never ſeem'd to make doubt of the paſſion I had to ſerve you; I complaine then with reaſon, becauſe your Reproaches are without reaſon, and beſeech you take the Paines hereafter to ponder the informations which ſhall be made you of a buſineſſe ſo Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant as this, and particularly when it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the Intereſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:36"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Doe ſo highly approve of your Iudgement, that I begin to queſtion my Innocence, ſince it has declared her culpable: yet I muſt aſſure you, with your Permiſſion, that my Thoughts did never contribute any thing to the fault whereof you accuſe me, and likewiſe condemne mee, without hearing me ſpeake. But though my misfortune were alwayes ſuch that you ſhould never incline to doe mee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet my conſcience ſhould alwayes, that I may reſt in Quiet, and peaceably poſſeſſe the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15760:36"/>
               <head>Congratulatory Letters to a new Married Man.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Reioyce extreamely at the Happy election you have made of a wife, ſince I par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate with Civility in the ſatisfaction which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: being glad that you have now divided the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which you had acquired over my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as honouring at this Preſent your deare halfe, with the ſame reſpects that heretofore I rendred to you onely. I will perſwade my ſelfe, you will make no doubt of it, no more then of the Paſſion I have to your Service, In Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble Servant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:37"/>
               <head>Another upon the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>DOe not expect that I ſhould formally congratulate with you the good-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of your Marriage, ſince I intereſſe my ſelfe in all your contentments. It ſufficeth me to put you in minde, that your good and ill fortune, ſhall be the ſole cauſe of all my joyes and diſcontents, as fully reſolved to follow, your Reſentments, in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:15760:37"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters of Congratulation.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Alwayes beleev'd that you loved me ſo much as to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate in my Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they are effects of your good nature and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, to which I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely Obliged. But I can aſſure you, that in the Election I have made of a Wife, you have obtained a new ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, ſince ſhe partakes already in the Paſſion, which I have to ſerve you, being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:38"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Know you are ſo Generous that you Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe your ſelfe in all things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne mee, but I am aſhamed of receiving daily new proofes, ſince I cannot Encounter with a fit Occaſion to revenge my ſelfe. All that I can ſay then is, that I ſhall have the ſame reſentment in all affaires, which ſhall touch your Particular, as being by Inclination as well as reaſon,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:15760:38"/>
               <head>Letters of Proteſtation of Friendſhip.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I have made a vow to bee your moſt perfect honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer all my life, and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit one poynt of the Paſſion which I have to doe you Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, yet I ſhall never Content my ſelfe, except ſome occaſion be offered very ſuddenly, whereby theſe Words may be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into effects. 'Tis the onely Good Fortune which I expect with Impatience, being not a little grieved that I beare in vaine the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your very humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:39"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>DOe not wonder if I importune you ſo often with my Letters, I have no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pleaſure in the World then to aſſure you of the eſteeme I make of your friendſhip, and the eternity of minde. 'Tis true, theſe are but words, but being they are dictated by my heart, I am ſatisfied in acquitting my ſelfe of that which I owe you. If occaſions to doe you ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would offer themſelves as often as they doe, to write to you, I would give Teſtimony by my actions, rather then my Diſcourſe, that I was never in Complement</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce my ill fortune deprives mee of occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to ſerve you, I muſt for my owne ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction witneſſe unto you the Paſſion which predominates in me. I know your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and Condition have acquired you ſervants without number, but I can aſſure you with as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15760:39"/>
much oſtentation, as Reaſon, that Ioyne them all together, I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>The moſt humble and moſt obedient.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe inclination which I have to eſteeme you more then all the World, will not ſuffer mee to let any opportunity ſlip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without giving you new aſſurances of this Truth. Not that I ceaſe to bee in a continuall impatiency, of expecting occaſions to give you more effectuall proofes, but becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not dependant of my will, I ſatisfie my ſelfe, in letting you know that ſhee ſhall never force to other thing, then to make open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:40"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters Protesting Friendſhip.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E as frequent as you pleaſe in giving me new aſſurances of your friendſhip, all the proofes that you can have of mine, cannot render it more perfect then it is: being I can aſſure you, that if my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours could take effect, or my vowes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, you ſhould not long account mee in the number of your unprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, though</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt obedient, and moſt faithfull.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="a" facs="tcp:15760:40"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Will never refuſe the Honour which you doe me in profeſſing to love me extreame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but ſince I have no merit to oblige you thereunto I dare not publiſh my good fortune, iuſtly fearing to bee deprived of it every Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Not becauſe I beleeve you will proove fickle, but reaſonable, and that therefore your Reaſon may oblige you, to make me loſe this good fortune, which mine onely and your Courteſie acquired me. But whatſoever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen I ſhall never be other</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Then your moſt humble and moſt obedient ſervant</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THough I never made doubt of your friendſhip, yet I make ſuch eſteeme thereof, that you advance me to a new degree of Honour and delight, every time you take the Paines to give mee freſh aſſurances of it by your letters. 'Tis true, in this you doe but
<pb facs="tcp:15760:41"/>
aſſure mine, yet howſoever, the commerce of this kind of entertainment is ſo delightful, that if I did not apprehend I might be importune, I ſhould write unto you by every opportunity that preſented it ſelfe, being 'tis the onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation which I have in your abſence, to put you in minde, that I will be eternally</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>FOR all you love me and eſteeme me ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much, you are ſtill indebted to me, ſince my object is your deſert: what proofes ſoever you give me of your friendſhip, they are not able to diminiſh the price of mine, being in a height of Perfection not to be valued. But if my misfortune nouriſh you in a continuall doubt, I will produce my advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage when you produce your aſſurances: Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nothing ſo much as to witneſſe unto you by effects rather then words, that I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="b" facs="tcp:15760:41"/>
               <head>Letters to a Friend in favour of another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He bearer of this Letter, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and one of my very good friends, deſiring that I would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you, (as I doe moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,) to oblige him in a buſineſſe whoſe ſucceſſe depends wholly in your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, I knew not how to refuſe his merit and condition ſo poore a Demand: wherefore you ſhall oblige me extreamely, if you will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to imploy ſome part of your credit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, without any other Conſideration, but only that you were Requeſted</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>by one of <hi>Your moſt humble, and moſt obedient ſervants,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:42"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Deſert, and Condition, have made you ſo Conſiderable and Neceſſary, that your friends are alwayes ſubject to importune you: and amongſt the reſt I at this Preſent, in favour of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who beares this Letter: beſeeching you, to ſupport him with your credit, in a buſineſſe of which hee will informe you. I ſhall account his obligations, into the Number of mine, and Teſtifie to you in my owne Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the Reſentment which I ſhall conceive in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Of Your moſt humble and moſt obedient ſervant.</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="c" facs="tcp:15760:42"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters of Favour.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Gentleman in whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe you tooke the Paines to write unto mee, will tell you by word of mouth, how faithfully I have ſerved you, in obliging him. If you judge mee able to render you any other ſervice, wherein I may finde more ſatisfaction, as prooving it more difficult, it ſtands upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but your ſelfe, to give mee the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being very glad to witneſſe unto you at all times how much I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:43"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Eſteeme my ſelfe happy to have met with this little occaſion, to doe you ſervice by making your friends buſineſſe (wherof you writ unto mee) bee determined to his advan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage. I imployed in it equally, both my Care and induſtry, not looſing one moment of time, to the end that I might thereby witneſſe, in what eſteeme I have the honour of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. You may give mee new ones when you pleaſe: if you deſire new proofes of the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble, and moſt faithfull ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="d" facs="tcp:15760:43"/>
               <head>Letters complaining of the Abſence of a Friend.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough true friendſhip bee in the Proofe of abſence, yet yours is of ſo long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that I imagine you pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to caſt me off, ſince you ſeeme to retire your affection thus by little and little. I ſpeake confidently, becauſe I feare extreamely, and you ought to pardon thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> boldneſſe and feare, ſince they proceed equally from the good inclination I have to your Service, and the great eſteeme I make of your Friendſhip. Returne then quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if you will free from ſorrow and diſquiet,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>The moſt humble of all your ſervants and the moſt faithfull.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:44"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Can endure your abſence no longer: you muſt of neceſſity ſhew your ſelfe oftner then you doe to your friend, for your owne honour, and my ſatisfaction: I ſay for your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, becauſe it is thereby in Queſtion, ſince you keepe your ſelfe ſo long retired in a place, of which even the Gazette never makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. You muſt not give ſo much way to your humour, and inclination, that they intereſſe with them the Contentment, of all that love you. For my owne part, I am reſolved to goe ſeeke you, if you returne not very ſoone, to which I adjure you, by all the Charmes of the Paſſion which I have to your ſervice, as being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:15760:44"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of Abſence.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou chide me with ſuch a good grace, that I could wiſh to ſee you oftner in that humor, ſince it obliges me to beleeve that I am not altogether indifferent to you. 'Tis true, my abſence hath been ſomething long, but being my preſence is unprofitable to my friends, by the diſability I am in to ſerve them, I make the leſſe account of my abſence from the Court; Yet the only means to occaſion my return, will be, if you teſtifie unto me that I can be uſefull to you when I am there; which ſhall precipitate my haſte, being in a firme reſolution to render you all manner of Service, in quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and obedient ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:15760:45"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY pride will become inſufferable, if you intereſſe your ſelfe often in the delay of my return. I wonder you can find me wanting at the Court where you have admirers without number; but if I could be perſwaded that my abſence did occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion your diſquiet, or that my preſence could be neceſſary for your ſervice, you ſhould not be able to detain me from the Town, whither your Commands ſhall ſoon call me when you are pleaſed to expect proofes of my obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters to cleare our ſelfes of a falſe report.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Need not much eloquence to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my innocency touching the report which was made to you of late, ſince I will oblige my ſelfe to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15760:45"/>
make them confeſſe the truth publickly that have been too ſhameleſſe to maintain the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in private. 'Tis a malice ſo ill contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, (though black as Hell) that I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it will deceive it ſelfe. For what appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is there, that having received an infinity of favour from your goodneſſe, I ſhould ſo irreverently contemne a thouſand other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble qualities that elevate your eſteem above the common? I beſeech you beleeve that I ſhall be their admirers all my life, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall flaile to the broachers of this Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. I have no reſpect of perſons when my Honor is queſtioned; I beare a ſword to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it with the hazard of my life, which I eſteem far leſſe. But if this cannot give you ſatisfaction, let me know the name of the reporter, and I will make you ſport in laying open the particulars of his knavery, and the ſincerity of my innocency, which ſhall give you ſufficient never to make doubt of the paſſion I have to ſerve you, as being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and obedient ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:15760:46"/>
               <head>An other.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT is an eaſie matter for any Man to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me, but I defie all the World toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to convince me in the leaſt reſpect. Tis true, I could not ſpeak in that Company, but ſome muſt heare me; but, be pleaſed to ſhew me my adverſary, and Ile engage my ſelf to make him ſigne me an acquittance of my innocency with his owne blood. I boaſt of nothing that I will not doe; for let me but know the broachers of that impoſture: and I will eaſily let you know their malice, which ſhall force you to beleeve (as I moſt humbly intreat you) that I will ſooner looſe my life than the honour and ſtile of being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obedient ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An other.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Will not juſtifie my ſelfe with words, of the aſperſion laid upon me, deſiring by ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects to let you ſee my innocency as clear,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15760:46"/>
as the malice of thoſe that would have blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it, black and pernicious. I beſeech you think that I ſhall never be able to forget the reſpect I owe you; and if any have the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to accuſe me of it, my Sword ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them a moſt rigorous pennance, ſince I profer to be alwayes what I alwayes was</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to the Letter of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is true, I was told you abuſed mee behind my back; but ſince I never gave you cauſe, and on the other ſide your diſcretion being ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently knowne to me, I was not ſo much as tempted to give credit to it; you needed not then have juſtified your ſelfe of a fault where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I eſteem'd you alwayes innocent. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation you bear in all places of the World, may ſeem as a judge to condemne your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15760:47"/>
wherefore you may ſleep in quiet, ſince I account my ſelfe diſintereſſed, and place me in the number</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble, and moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſervants.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BEfore I can declare you guilty, you muſt confeſſe your ſelf faulty with your own mouth; for the teſtimonies of all the World, cannot convince the good opinion I have of your integrity. Men may calumniate your reputation as much as they pleaſe, but I ſhall alwayes hold your accuſers to be in the fault, ſince it is impoſſible I ſhould loſe the eſteem which I conceive of your deſert, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:15760:47"/>
               <head>Letters to a ſick Friend.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He news of your ſickneſſe hath bred ſuch a change in my health, that I may juſtly count my ſelfe in the number of thoſe that are not well. Take courage then, if you will give it me; you know the intent I have in all things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your particular. In a word, if you leave not your bed very ſuddenly, I ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to take it. Theſe are the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your very humble ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Will not tell you how extreamely ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſorrowfull news of your ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was to me; only I muſt put you in mind that your diſeaſe cannot chuſe but be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15760:48"/>
very contagious, having infected one hither. I could wiſh, for your ſervice and my content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I were neare you; but my miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is ſuch, that it ties me to certain affaires in this Town, which by no meanes I am able to abandon. Yet all theſe obſtacles ſhall not hinder me from acquitting my ſelfe of my duty, if you eſteem me uſefull to render you any manner of ſervice, of which I give you moſt faithfull aſſurance, as proteſting to be all my life,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters written to a ſick Friend.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I had ſooner recovered my health, I had ſooner returned you thanks for the reſentment you wittneſſed to have of my ſicknes: but being it kept me very long, I was conſtrained to delay my acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment till this very preſent: though 'tis not from this encounter onely that I know how ſenſible you are of al things concerning your Friends, which makes you have them without
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15760:48"/>
number; but I can aſſure you, that put them all together, I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>The moſt obedient and moſt faithfull.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An other Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AS ſoon as ever I was able to hold a pen, I ſerved my ſelf of the opportunity to render you thanks, for the conſolation which you gave me, in the delightfull enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of your letters. Yet, I pray you Sir, deprive me not of this contentment, if you would not have me ſick againe. For I can aſſure you, tis a very great ſatiſfaction to me to ſee my ſelfe honoured with the favour of your remembrance, in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:15760:49"/>
               <head>Letters to demand the protection of a ſtrange Prince.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I have not the honour to be knowne to your Highneſſe, yet the eſteem that al the World makes of your Royall vertues, gave me the boldneſſe moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to beſeech your Majeſtie to grant me protection within the Lands of your Obedience. I am not guilty of any crime that ſhould make me bluſh; and if I have violated the Lawes of my owne Prince, it was but to obey the Law which Honour had impoſed upon me before. This makes me expect from your Highnes bounty, al manner of aſſiſtance, ſince onely the profeſſion of Souldier made me quit my owne Country. Your Highneſſe will augment by this action the number of your Creatures, ſince thereby I ſhall vow my ſelfe to live and dye in quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your Highneſſe Moſt humble ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:15760:49"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Bruit of your Highneſſe renowne occaſion'd my entrance into the Lands of your Obedience, not knowing where to find a more aſſured harbour in the World. I hope your Highneſſe will not violate for me alone, the Lawes which your wiſedome has already made in favour of diſtreſſed and guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſons; and though I be no otherwiſe than the right of Honour dos permit, yet I moſt humbly implore your Majeſties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection as extreamly conducing to my repoſe and quiet. For my birth and condition, I thought it not neceſſary to reveale them, till your Highneſſe command oblige me to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficient to give you aſſurance, that I have committed no crime whereof all men that make profeſſion of Honour, may not be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuſed and convicted together; But I will be all my life</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Highneſſe Moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:15760:50"/>
               <head>Letters witnesſing unto a Friend the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment we receive in ſerving him.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Should expreſſe but one part of my Contentment, though I ſhould ſay in doing you ſervice I receive all the ſatiſfaction the World is able to afford; for your merit is ſo conſiderable, that there is no divertiſment like the continuall action of executing your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Doe not think that I complement, but beleeve infallibly that my heart, mouth, and pen, conſpire together every time I give you aſſurance, as I doe now, that I am more than all the World.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An other.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu are ſo generous that you know by experience what contentment men receive in doing their friends ſervice;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15760:50"/>
for my owne particular, I think nothing can be added to mine, ſuch a ſenſible feeling I have of it every time you are pleaſed to honour me with your commands. I pray you then be not ſo ſparing, ſince it is my whole delight, and ſince I ſhall importune you for nothing elſe, in the reſolution I have taken, to beare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my grave, the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Never eſteem'd my ſelfe happy till the day wherein you were pleaſed to give mee an employment for your ſervice, as being the only thing in the world I aſpir'd to with moſt paſſion. I would you were alwayes in th' hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to honour me with your commands, as I am alwayes to obey them, which you ſhall doe me a great favour to beleeve, and beſides
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15760:51"/>
that I am unfeignedly and without reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt faithfull ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to the precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very time you are pleaſed to give me ſure teſtimonies of your friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, I find my ſelfe moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully touched by my ordinary im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, of incountring with ſome opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to revenge my ſelfe; but ſince you are extreamly reaſonable, I will force my ſelfe to beleeve, that you conſider rather the price of my zeale, than the misfortune of my diſabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo that making no doubt of the paſſion I beare to your ſervice, you will place mee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the rank</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt obedient and moſt faithfull ſervants,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:15760:51"/>
               <head>An other Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Know 'tis your ordinary delight to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige all the World, without expecting as much as thanks; but I beſeech you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that I am too honeſtly envious of your nobleneſſe, that every time you are pleaſed to give me new proofes thereof, I live in all the tortures of the World, till I have encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with the means of requiting it. And finding my ſelfe in that caſe at this preſent, I am forced to repreſent unto you my diſquiet, that I may not be accuſed of ingratitude, and leſſe of negligence, in ſeeking occaſions to teſtifie unto you how perfectly I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and obliged ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An other Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>'TIs not enough to oblige continually your friends; friendſhip commands that you ſhould ſerve your ſelfe of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15760:52"/>
them, in all kind of encounters; to which I conjure you, if you deſire I ſhould beleeve that you love me extreamely. I will never importune you with other things, in the grief I remain, to beare unprofitably, the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and obedient ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT would be very hard for me to expreſſe how ſtrictly I am yours; for what proofes ſoever my obedience were able to give you, they could reſent but one part of the paſſion which I have to your ſervice, as being, inimitably</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and faithfull ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An other Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am reſolved to beſeech you would be pleaſed to honour mee continually with your commands, ſince you are pleaſed to produce continually new proofes of your
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15760:52"/>
friendſhip. Theſe ſhall be all the intreaties I will make you, to the end that my obedience may ſerve me for an occaſion, in ſerving you according to the paſſion which raignes in me. And to witneſſe unto you, that there be few in the World can vaunt with reaſon, that they are to that height as I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT would be very hard for mee to reckon up the obligations which I have to you; You are too noble in all reſpects, (and eſpecially when it ſtands upon the intereſts of your friends) that it is ſufficiently ſeene you take great pleaſure in having no equall. Yet I muſt tell you freely, that I am one of your Enviers, as well as of your Admirers, being Jealous of the continuall Generoſity you exerciſe in my behalfe, not leaving mee ſo much leaſure as to ruminate upon the means of acknowledgement. 'Tis my turne now to let you know, I am not inſenſible, and that if you be extreamly well skill'd in the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15760:53"/>
Art of obliging all the World, I am not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ignorant of the Art of acquitting my ſelfe. I beſeech you beleeve it, and that I am without Complement</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Begin to grow weary of your favours; the diſability in which I find my ſelfe, will not ſuffer me to receive any new one, for feare I ſhould be conſtrain'd in the End to paſſe for Ungratefull. Wherefore except I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with ſome favourable occaſion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I may witneſſe the Paſſion which I have to ſerve you, I will never adde any thing to this number of obligations. This is my Humor, my Reſolution being to profeſſe my ſelfe all my Life</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15760:53"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART OF The Secretarie in Faſhion.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15760:54"/>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:15760:54"/>
               <head>A Letter Conſolatory to a <hi>Father upon the Death of his Sonne.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſorrowfull newes of your Sonnes Death, touched mee very feelingly, and the more, becauſe I had the honour of his acquaintance, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar knowledge of his Deſerts. The love which you have ſuſtain'd, is very great I confeſſe; but you muſt likewiſe confeſſe that unavoydable evils, are to be endured with conſtancy. I ſpeak not this to condemne your Sighes and Teares, for I doe willingly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of them, yea, even in exceſſe: but to let you know, that after you have ſatisfied your humour, you muſt a little give place to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, being you ſhall receive as much glory in drying vp your Teares, as you did once plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in ſhedding them. I know your Sonne
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15760:55"/>
was the onely Comfort which remained to you in this World, and that his preſence meerly did make you live contented even amongſt the peeviſhneſſes of old age. But all this induceth mee to beleeve that God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived you of him, for no other Reaſon, but onely to comfort you hereafter in himſelfe, as being the onely Good which is ſubject to no Change. He calls himſelfe a Jealous God; wonder not then if he be Jealous of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſureable love you bore to your Childe. And if his Providence hath found a meanes to oblige you, in robbing you of an object which poſſeſt all your affections together, you on the other ſide are obliged this Day to make him the object of your Thankſgiving, and not of your Complaints. This is that which I expect at the hands of your Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, and ſoundneſſe of Judgement; the weakeneſſe of mine, detaining mee from paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing further, being aſſured that you are able your ſelfe to be your own Comforter. It ſufficeth me that I acquit my ſelfe of my Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in witneſſing to you the griefe I conceive for your Misfortune, and the continuall care I ſhall have to blaze my ſelfe whereſoever I come,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:15760:55"/>
               <head>The Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am obliged to you, for the charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble counſell you were pleaſed to give me upon the Death of my Sonne: But ſuffer me to tell you (after my humble thanks) that my affliction is of ſuch a Nature, that Death only is able to give me ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, ſo that I find my ſelfe conſtrained to go ſeek my remedy in my Grave; and yet I doe not murmure againſt the providence of God; though I muſt aſſure you that without a particular Grace, and ſenſible miracle, I ſhall faint under the burden of my misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. Yet I beſeech you Sir, doe not deprive mee of the Comfor of your Letters, knowing I cannot enjoy the Happineſſe of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: And above all things, remember me in your Prayers, ſince I expect no ſuccour but from Heaven. I am ever</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15760:56"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur deare Letter concerning the death of my Sonne, had much allayd my Greife, if my affliction had been ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any Comfort; Yet I eſteeme my ſelf extreamly obliged to you for the part you ſeem to take in my Misfortune, in which you teſtifie that you are equally both of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Diſpoſition, and a Good Friend. Sir, the ſorrow which oppreſſeth me, has left mee nothing but ſighes and teares to offer you up in acknowledgement, it ſufficeing mee (ſince it is true) that you beleeve I am and will be everlaſtingly</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your very humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters Conſolatory to a Sonne, upon the Death of his Father.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Had ſooner condoled with you the loſſe of your Father, if I had ſooner judged you capable of Conſolation. I thought it fit to afford you ſome
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15760:56"/>
time, to pay (with the abundance of your Teares) the debt you owed to Nature; but now having ſatisfied your ſelfe, by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Teſtimony which you have given of your Sorrow, I come amongſt others, to acquit my ſelfe of my obligation, and to perſwade you to patience, aſſuring you that I am very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the exceſſe of your Affliction. I know you have practiſed that vertue in a thouſand Encounters of Misfortune, which have made you able to give leſſons to all the reſt of the World; So that all I am to doe, is to put you in mind, that both you and I make all the haſte poſſible after him whoſe abſence we deplore with too much Lamentation; and that without a particular Favour of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, we ſhall be even at his heeles, before we be worthily prepared for ſo great a Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. This I made bold to remember you of, and likewiſe that I am, as much as ever</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Letter.</head>
               <p>TIs not to Comfort you of the loſſe which you have ſuſtained, that I put Pen to Paper, but rather to give Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15760:57"/>
of the Reſentment which I feele, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ability of your judgement, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my owne. It ſufficeth mee to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto you, that in the Neceſſity of dying or being born, Nature does oblige every man to goe the Way that is Marked out for him; Tis no matter how long and ſtrong ſome men be, they all meet together at the Grave, and being arived there, none makes account of the Time which they imployed in going that Voyage. For our owne particulars, let us conſider how many yeares we have already ſpent ſince we began it; and in this very Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that you read this, we may propoſe to our ſelves the End of it, by the Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a hidden death. As for your Father, he dyed but for himſelfe, and has perhaps left you a while to play his Part here in this World, which ought in my opinion to leave you more Envy than Sorrow, knowing that he has already caſt Anchor in that haven whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you tend with might and maine. I would ſay more, if I made no conſcience to detaine your Eyes too long upon this Paper; you muſt give them yet a little time to ſleepe, ſince your Griefe is juſt; in which I take a large Part, in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:15760:57"/>
               <head>Another Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am too much your Servant, to remaine Dumbe, and Inſenſible, at the ſorrowfull report of your Fathers death. Theſe lines in acquitting me of what I owe you, wil teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie unto you the Part I take in your affliction. I think it will be hard for you to comfort your ſelfe after ſuch a Loſſe; but ſince God does never Afflict us above our force, let the force of your judgement work your Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The moſt ſweet conſideration you can have, is that you were witneſſe of the laſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which your Father did, before his retreat, out of this World; which having either few or no examples, may be a ſufficient cauſe of your Quiet, every time you conſider their importance. Live honeſtly as he did, and dye in the ſame Manner; you are in the right way to the Place whither he is gone: and if he have anticipated you ſome few dayes, thoſe will ſeeme but a Moment, when you are arived at the End. Solace your ſelfe then in his abſence, ſince the innocency wherein you live, is an Infallible Aſſurance to you that you ſhall ſee him very ſuddenly. I will give you like undoubted Teſtimony of the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15760:58"/>
Paſſion which I have to your Service, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you pleaſe to honour mee with your Commands, as being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to the Letters of Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe not excuſe the Long time that I have ſtaid in returning you thanks for the part which you did mee the Honour to take in my affliction; becauſe the Griefe is ſtill ſo ſenſible to mee, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imploy my Spirit without Violence, in any other thoughts but thoſe of my Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune: Not that I remaine not entirely Reſigned to the Wil of God, and fully Reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to Patience: but yet all this cannot hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Sorrow from Enjoying an abſolute Poſſeſſion of mee: and for an Encreaſe of Miſchiefe, my griefe-ſick Humour does ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſo agreeable, that I have not ſo much Liberty as to Complaine, though it devour me by Little and Little. Yet I ceaſe not to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15760:58"/>
be extreamly obliged to you, for your Pious and Charitable Counſells, which you were pleaſed to give mee, aſſureing you that I will take my ordinary Leſſons of Comfort out of them. Notwithſtanding, I muſt tell you with my ancient freedom, that as my Affliction comes from above, 'tis from thence onely that I expect a Remedy. How good a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian ſoever Time be, I deſire nothing of you but Prayers, intermingled with Commands; to the end that my obedience may make mee worthy the good opinion you have</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Muſt confeſſe your Charitable letter did much comfort the loſſe which I lately ſuſtained; and the more, becauſe it gave Teſtimony of your feeling in my Affliction. In ſuch accidents as theſe, I never find more Conſolation, than to ſee my ſelfe lamented by my Friends; amongſt whom ſince you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the firſt rank, I leave to your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whether your Letter were agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15760:59"/>
to me, or no: Yet for all that, I cannot ceaſe my Teares, my Sorrow increaſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee daily more and more, through the Remembrance of the Miſfortune which was the cauſe of it. And truly after this Loſſe, I cannot apprehend any other; which might ſerve me for a very effectuall admoniſhment, if I were Capable of receiving any. I would ſay more, if my Teares did not blot out my Writing: Wherefore in briefe, I doe deſire of you, that you would be pleaſed to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me the Honour of your Remembrance, and adde not the Loſſe of your Friendſhip to this which I already ſuſtaine; ſince I am with Paſſion</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obliged ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters Conſolatory to a Husband upon the Death of his Wife.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know not in what Tearmes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to comfort you, your Loſſe appearing to mee ſo great, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the exceſſe of your Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15760:59"/>
and my Reſentment, that I am farre more diſpoſed to accompany your teares, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any way to ſolace your Miſery. You know Misfortune has taught mee by Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience to value a Diſcontent of that Nature, having heretofore ſhed teares for the ſame ſubject. So that repreſenting to my ſelfe that which I have ſuffered in a like Incounter, I muſt needs tell you, you are not to expect your Remedy from any Place but Heaven. Though I deny not but Time may worke much upon that kind of Malady; yet the Terme is ſo long, that the little remainder of Quiet, which is left after the Purge of our diſcontent, ſtays not ſo long as to give us an abſolute and full Poſſeſſion of it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be aſſured, that God will not abandon you, if you adore his Providence with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; a Meanes to which, is, if you Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that you are continually in Election to ſee your Wife againe, and ſooner too than perhaps you imagine. Pardon mee Sir, for my freedome of ſpeech; I cannot flatter you, being to that Point, as I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:15760:60"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THough I be not able to Comfort you in your Wifes death, yet it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for my ſatisfaction, that I witnes unto you the great part which I take in your Affliction: onely I will put you in Minde, that in Sorrowfull Accidents, Patience is the cheif Remedy, after our Reſignation to the Will of God. Our teares and Complaints are in vaine, ſince they doe but provoke Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in ſtead of appeaſing it. When you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed that vertuous Lady, the Notary who paſſed the Contract of your Marriage, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got not to inſert this Clauſe, that the ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor ſhould enjoy the rights of Widdowſhip. What reaſon have you then, to lament a Death which you foreſaw ſo long ſince, as if you had been aſſured, when you tooke her, ſhee had not been ſubject to it? She preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you in an Inevitable Action; and perhaps it will not be much; Ten yeares more or leſſe, are but an inſtant to that of Death; For which I would wiſh you prepare your ſelfe; what leaſure ſoever you have, I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you you will have very little ſpare time. But I muſt not incurre the Fault from which I promiſed to exempt my ſelfe. I aske you
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15760:60"/>
Pardon, ſince my Crime is occaſioned by my Zeale, as being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Friendſhip and ſervice I vowed to you long agoe, have made mee ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the ſorrowfull Newes of your Wifes death, that I ſtand in need of the Conſolation which all the World does ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter to you. Expect not then any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from mee, being afflicted as I am. All that I can ſay to you, is, that your Wife dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that innocency, in which ſhee alwayes lived, has left you in my Opinion a greater cauſe of Envy, than of Sorrow. Wherefore, I would not have you Dreame of any thing ſo much, as of following her; and ſince you are every houre haſtening to your end, change the Nature of your teares, lamenting more that ſhe has left you behind her, than that ſhe is gone before you. This is all the Counſell I can give you, together with a new aſſurance that I will live and dye</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:15760:61"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Griefe which I conceived for the loſſe of my Wife, would not permit mee ſooner to render you thanks, for the pious reſentment you witneſſe in her behalfe. I always thought you would participate in my Misfortunes, becauſe you did mee the Honour to love mee: And the rather becauſe I knew you were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in my Sorrow, as having loſt a moſt humble Servant. Yet I remaine indebted to you for the Charitable care which you took in comforting mee, though it were in vaine, ſince I cannot ſo ſoone quit the memory of a Loſſe ſo important to my repoſe. Men may tell me as much as they pleaſe, that my Miſery is without reliefe; 'tis becauſe of that that I am void of Comfort. To cure it, is a work of the Hand of God; and all that Time and my Friends are able to contribute, does but ſerve to diſpoſe the matter, which the Almighty muſt informe when he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. Yet Sir, though my Misfortunes be in their Flood, they have not drowned the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfull
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15760:61"/>
obſervance I alwayes uſed in your behalfe, as having made a vow to coffin up with my ſelfe the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt faithfull ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Could heartily wiſh, that the Sorrow I conceive for my Wifes death, were capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Conſolation, that ſo I might make uſe of the Charitable precepts you were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give me, for which I render you moſt humble thanks: But truly Sir, my Affliction is ſo great, that if God doe not ſoone play the Phyſitian, I can expect remedy from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death. So that how conſtantly ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I beare my Misfortune, the very Sorrow wherewith it is accompanied, will thruſt me by little and little into my Grave. Not that I have not wholly reſigned my ſelfe to the will of God, but becauſe being not able to make this Reſignation in all points abſolute, the remainder of my Liberty ſerves to no other end but to torment me: Make your
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15760:62"/>
Prayers to Heaven for me, that it would pleaſe to conduct mee ſuddenly into that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Quiet where you now are: I expect of your devotion, this favour from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine goodneſſe, as you ohght to expect all manner of ſervice from the friendſhip I have vowed to you, as being with Paſſion</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Can thank you for nothing but your good will which you witneſſed to me, in thoſe wholeſome counſels you were pleaſed to give me touching the Loſſe which I have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſtain'd; For how powerfull ſoever your reaſons be, they can never leſſen my ſorrow, and much leſſe be able to heale it. Thoſe that ſee my Misfortune, conſider it but as an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident that arrives every day, and which tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at the ſame time an infinite number of Husbands: but if they could penetrate into the bottome of my Soule, that they might know the juſt cauſe of my continual lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the wiſeſt of them would be conſtraind to approve the Eternity of my complaints,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15760:62"/>
ſince they would know thereby how hopeleſſe they are of cure. 'Tis true there is nothing elſe now able to give me ſatisfaction, which makes me find ſome kind of Comfort in the ſhortning of my dayes, ſince I ſolace my ſelfe in my departure, knowing it tends to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of my Griefe. Youle tell me perhaps I ſpeak not like a Chriſtian; I am one howſoever; but the Affliction to which I have abandond my ſelfe, will not ſuffer me to enjoy any other Light, than that which ſhows the way to my Grave. I returne to the obligation wherein I am bound to you for the Honour of your Remembrance and charitable admonitions, and to witneſſe unto you the Reſentment they have left in me in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Confeſſe the Admonitions which you u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the laſt letter wherewith you were pleaſed to honour mee, touching the loſſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15760:63"/>
which I have ſuſtained of late, by the Death of my Wife, were ſo Ponderous, that I could not chuſe but receive thereby great Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis needfull (as you ſay very well) that our firſt leſſon of Conſtancy, ſhould be the reſignation of our wils to God: and that al the Study which we are to imploy therein, ſhould be but to perfect that Action. I acknowledge it very willingly; the experience which I have learn'd, will ſuffer mee to make no further doubt. For God laid the Affliction upon me, and he himſelfe is my Comforter. His Juſtice puniſhed me, but his Goodneſſe has made me find ſo much ſweetnes in my Miſery, that in ſtead of Complaints, I am bound to render him Everlaſting Thankſgiving. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, continue me the Favour of your good Counſels, with the Honour of your Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and beleeve if you pleaſe, that I will be all my life,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:15760:63"/>
               <head>Conſolatory Letters to a Lady or Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man upon her Husbands Death.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had no ſooner heard the ſorrowfull newes of your Husbands death, but I put Pen to paper, to witneſſe unto you at the ſame time, both the Sorrow which I conceive, and the Reſolution which I have taken to die in your Ladyſhips ſervice. If I thought my ſelfe able to comfort you, I would do my endeavour moſt freely; but the Remembrance of your Vertue forbids mee, ſince it alone is ſufficient to give you the Leſſons, which it made you practice hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in other encounters of Misfortune. Tis true, this is more penetrating than all the reſt; therefore your Conſtancy ſhould employ all her Endeavours to ſurmount your Griefe: and ſince Grace onely can give us the greateſt part of our force, you have more (in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) to hope for than to feare, in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. What if Heaven be provoked againſt us; it never afrights us with the noyſe of his Thunder, but it rejoyceth us very ſuddenly with the cleare ſhining light of his Sunnes beames. But if you be preſſed with impatience
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15760:64"/>
in this Surpriſall of Sorrow, dry up your teares, ceaſe the continuation of your Sighs, you ſhall find the Soveraigne Remedy of all your Ills, in the practice of theſe actions. Mine ſhall be alwaies directed to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Service, as being from my heart ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Mouth,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Find in my ſelfe a greater diſpoſition to lament with you the loſſe which you have ſuſtained, than I judge my ſelfe able to give you comfort. For if you be deprived of a Husband whom you loved intirely, I am rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of a Friend for whom I would have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured a thouſand Lives. Truly Madam, I am ſo wholly taken up in my own Sighes, and teares, that I cannot think of yours, but in ſome intermediating Houres, be they never ſo extreame. So that in ſtead of giving you Comfort, I am more like to perſwade you to render your Complaints Everlaſting. You may ſeek an other Husband to a faire purpoſe,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15760:64"/>
the World is too narrow to find his Equall. And for my ſelfe, I may truly ſay, the mould of my old Friend being broken, I ſhould ſpend my Travaile in vaine, if I went about to parallell him amongſt my new ones. Let us then ſolace our ſelves in our affliction Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſince it is extreame: the Extremity of it will ſoone teach us the way to our Graves where wee ſhall find a Remedy for our ills. If it be lawfull to love perfectly, no man wil hinder us to lament without ceaſe, ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall tears are the Teſtimonies of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Love. In the caſe I am in at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I am able to give you no other advice; yet if God give you the Grace to deſpiſe my Counſell, I ſhall never reproach you for it, but rather beſeech you that you would make your Prayers to God, for my like happineſſe, and to beleeve that if I be extreamly afflicted, I am no leſſe</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAving given you a thouſand Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the particular eſteem I made of your Husband, I hope you will
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15760:65"/>
not now doubt of the Reſentment which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines to mee for his Loſſe. Theſe lines notwithſtanding ſhal give you a new aſſurance of it, and likewiſe of the good will I have to doe you ſervice. If I were capable of giving Conſolation, I would begin with my ſelfe, being ſenſibly touched with the ſame affliction which torments you. But I leave that care to your Judgment and Vertue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the ſtrength of the one will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my weakneſſe, and the precepts of the other will exceed all the Counſell and advice I can impart to you. Beſides knowing you to be wholly reſigned to the Will of God, that Reſignation will be the ſoveraigne remedy of your diſtreſſe. The Heavens doe alwayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us Comfort for the ills they ſend us; but they expect ſubmiſſion, to make us wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of that favour which I hope you are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in ſtate to obtaine, it being the only Meanes to live at Quiet in the middle of Diſtreſſes; For my part, I will alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſe my ſelfe in yours, as being with Paſſion the ſame I alwayes was,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obedient ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:15760:65"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beleeve the Loſſe I ſuſtained in the death of my late Husband, does touch you very ſenſibly, ſince in your own particular you are robbed of a moſt real friend, and faithfull Servant: but for as my own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, my Affliction is ſo great, that if God do not comfort mee very ſuddenly, I ſhall die very ſuddenly of Griefe. You may judge by the ſtate I am in at this preſent, what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort I can expect from my Miſery; for, as my Fortune and Happineſſe are equally buried in my Husbands Grave, except he revive, I ſhall never be able to revive out of the Grave of Sadneſſe, and Diſcontent. All that I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in this extremity, is, to reſigne my ſelfe totally to the Will of God; and ſince your Prayers may be favourable to me in that behalf, I beſeech you for their continuation, for which I ſhall be indebted to you all my life, and in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:15760:66"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THrough my Teares, I read the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Letter which you did me the Honour to write unto me, touching the Death of my late Husband; and the little ſpace which I employed in drying them up, gave me time to render you thanks. I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to have writ more at large, when I took Pen in hand; but the ſorrow which I endure, will ſcarce give mee liberty to aſſure you that I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter from a Widdow, certifying a friend of her Husbands Death.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sorrowfull Letter ſhall inculcate nothing but death into your memory, aſſuring you that you have loſt a moſt reall admirer, and faithfull ſervant, in the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15760:66"/>
Perſon of my Husband. Pardon me if I ſay no more; the Pen fals out of my Hand, and my teares blot out my writing. I am the moſt afflicted Woman in the World,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>and <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter from a Husband to his Wife, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting her upon the Death of their Son.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>WIFE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is with an extreame Sorrow that I am conſtrain'd to trouble your Quiet at this preſent with newes which at the firſt view wil be able to beare you into your Accuſtomed extremity, if it be not ſupported by the Reſignation of your will to God. But knowing that you are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes diſpoſed to undergoe the Lawes of his Providence, I take the boldneſſe to let you know that that very Providence of God, has ſounded a retreat out of this World, to our eldeſt ſonne. This Accident, how new and ſtrange ſoever it ſeeme, muſt not ſoe ſtrictly ſeize upon you, that you murmur againſt the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15760:67"/>
Author. You muſt reſiſt the attempts of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row by my example; and after you have ſhed ſome Teares, which the Quality of Mother will conſtraine you to, you muſt adore (in drying them up) the Omnipotency of him that gave the blow; To the end that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double not his Wrath, in depriving us of the Comfort which as yet remaines with us. Doe not think that I am inſenſible at this Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; it touched me to the Quick; and the more, becauſe I am conſtrained to partake it with you. But ſince God has ordaind us to this Affliction, we ought to witneſſe by the Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our Complaints, that there is no exceſſe in his Chaſtiſment. I leave the thought of all theſe Conſiderations to your ſelf, with aſſurance that I remaine,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Deare Wife,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt faithfull Husband.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:15760:67"/>
               <head>LOVE LETTERS upon all ſorts of Subjects. <hi>And Firſt of Preſentation of Service.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE inclination which I have to eſteeme you more than all the reſt of the World, obliged mee at this Preſent, to offer your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip my moſt humble Service: And to aſſure you, that if you be pleaſed therewith, I ſhall never change the Reſolution, to be all my life</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obedient ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:15760:68"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Should not take the Liberty to let you know how extreamly I honour you, if the Abſolute power of your Beauty did not force me to it. Which relating unto you the violence it uſeth in my behalfe, will eaſily (I hope) obtaine Pardon for my Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. My deſire in this is no other but onely to know whether you be pleaſed I ſhould Everlaſtingly beare the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Could no longer conceale the Reſolution which I have taken, to ſerve you all my life, and beare the Character of your love eternally, if my Service and Love bee agreeable to you. You may ſignifie it to me, when you pleaſe, that I may have the Honor,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15760:68"/>
and Satisfaction to beare in Publick every where the Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Muſt of neceſſity for my owne Quiet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the deſire which I have, to love, and ſerve you, if you Judge mee worthy ſo great an honour. Your merit obliged mee, and my Inclination conſtrained mee to it. I expect only to know your will, that I may perfect my determination of profeſſing pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly the ſtile</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt obedient ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:15760:69"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am much obliged to you for the good will you witneſſe in my behalfe: but I have no other Liberty left mee, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to give you thanks, as I doe very hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: aſſuring you that I will conſerve your Remembrance for an acknowledgement, in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have nothing but thanks to offer up to you for the Honour you were pleaſed to doe mee in your laſt Letters. And though they be ordinary effects of your Civility, rather then Proofes of your love, yet I cannot chuſe but be extreamly obliged
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15760:69"/>
to you, which I beſeech you beleeve, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Doe not excuſe my ſelfe of not anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your laſt letter, becauſe my Wil does ſo abſolutely depend of my Parents incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that you are to learne of them, that which you deſire to know of mee. Yet your good will ſhall oblige mee to be in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, all my life,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu know that in the ſtate I am, I muſt neither accept nor refuſe the Offers which you make me, contenting my ſelfe to witneſſe unto you the Reſentment
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15760:70"/>
which they left in mee, with aſſurance that I honour ſo much the Merit of your Miſtreſſe that I ſhall alwayes preferre it before the Condition</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant,</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters to demand an Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Silence nouriſheth a Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all doubt in mee, whether my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice be acceptable or noe. You may Reſolve me when you pleaſe by ſome ſhort Anſwer, if you Judge me worthy the favour and Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble, and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:15760:70"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you knew with what impatience I expect the favour of your Reply, I aſſure my ſelfe your Charity would oblige you, to ſet my Mind at Quiet; But as that is an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which I muſt expect from your Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, rather than the Paſſion I have to your Service (not knowing whether it be agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to you or no) I muſt have recourſe to prayers, beſeeching you very humbly to vouchſafe an Anſwer, which may authorize the Quality, I beare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Reſolution I have taken to ſerve you all my life, does too far intereſſe my Repoſe, not to deſire your Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in that reſpect, I hope for this favour from your Goodneſſe, as you ought to expect
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15760:71"/>
from my duty, all manner of obſervance; being deſirous to live and die, if you bee pleaſed,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THis Letter is ſo Curious to learn newes of her former Companion, that ſhee would needs be gone in that Purſuit, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt againſt my wil. Let me know then if you pleaſe whether the firſt was acceptable or no, to the end that either I may continue you my ſervice, or ceaſe to be further importune. Theſe are the moſt humble prayers</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt obedient ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:15760:71"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Took the Liberty to write unto you, but not to reſolve you in your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. You know the Quality of Daughter does ſo ſubject mee, that I cannot violate the Reſpect I owe unto my Parents; yet I confeſſe my ſelfe much indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your good Nature, being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Was reſolved to keep ſilence, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what anſwer to give you; but ſince you require a letter, this ſhall tell you, that I have no other Reſolution than to honour you as your Merit does oblige me: And that in requitall of your Civility, I ſhall make my ſelfe accounted in all places</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:15760:72"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Send you this Letter, becauſe you deſire it, but it is only to aſſure you of the ſmall ability I have to ſatisfie your requeſt: You know you are to adreſſe your ſelfe to others then to me. Yet I beſeech you beleeve that I eſteem my ſelfe much Honoured in the teſtimony of your Affection, being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am obliged to you for two letters, but I muſt tell you for anſwer, that you are to expect no more from me, having no other liberty, but this only which I take to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you of it. I ſpeak not this becauſe I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Honour you are pleaſed to doe mee, but becauſe being extreamly ſenſible as I am, the Quality of Daughter affords me no more power, to publiſh the ſtile.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:15760:72"/>
               <head>Letters upon the abſence of ones Miſtreſſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving given you ſuch abſolute proofs of Love, as I have done, I hope you will make no doubt of the griefe which your Abſence cauſeth in mee: You can ſcarce beleeve the one, without give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing credit to the other; and this is the thing which gives me ſome kind of Comfort in my Affliction. If I durſt preſume to ſupplicate for your Returne, I would doe it with as much earneſtneſſe, as a Sick man would implore the preſence of his Phyſitian; ſince I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, yours is as neceſſary for my repoſe, having vowed to live and die</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:15760:73"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you knew, how ſenſible I were of your Abſence, you would ſcarce be able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend your ſelfe againſt the attempts of Pittie, how cruell ſoever you were by Nature. I ſuffer a Torment whoſe report only would force my Enemies to compaſſion, and yet can hardly beleeve that you regard it, being farre from imagining you are touched by it, in the leaſt reſpect. But ſince you were borne into the World for no other end, than to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, and I to endure all manner of miſerie, I muſt expect no Remedy but from Patience, and the Conſideration of the Quality which I beare</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant,</hi> M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another to the ſame Purpoſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have led ſo ſorrowfull a Life, ſince the Day of your Departure, that if I ſhould recount it to the moſt inſenſible ſoules of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15760:73"/>
the World, 'tis credible they would be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to Compaſſion. Yet I doe not deſire to ſtirre up that Paſſion in you, ſufficing my ſelfe that you take notice of it, to the End that you make no doubt of my Love, and leſſe of my Conſtancy. I muſt tell you then, that having loſt both my appetite and repoſe, I paſſe over whole daies without eating, and whole Nights without ſleep. I may ſeeke Contentment to a faire Purpoſe in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of my Friends, but I can find it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Solitude, where my thoughts as ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as your ſelfe to increaſe my Affliction, repreſent nothing to mee but your Cruelty. Judge now if I be not one of the moſt wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lovers in the World. Yet my Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is in this, that I ſuffer all theſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions for the moſt worthy Subject living, and for whom I would looſe a Thouſand Lives, as being</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, and moſt faithfull Lover.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF my Life be conſiderable to you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne very quickly, that I may be cured of a mortall ſickneſſe, which has ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15760:74"/>
me by reaſon of your Abſence. You ought to bee carefull in conſerving mee, in the Paſſion which I have to your Service, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there be few in the World can give ſo good a Teſtimony of your worth, to which long agoe I dedicated my ſelfe</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>A <hi>Moſt humble and obedient ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to the Precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oves diſeaſes are ſo eaſie to cure, that I never ſpend my Charity upon ſuch perſons. If you be ſurprized with that kind of Malady, my Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence (whereof you complaine) will ſoone afford you a Remedy: but if that ſhould not prove as I expect, then (to your owne advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage) the truth of your Affection wil appear by the continuance of your Conſtancy, which ſhall render me, as far as Liberty permits</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:15760:74"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu know I am not accuſtomed to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, the Complaints of Lovers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they dye ſo often in word and Appearance, that the report of their Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions does now paſſe for a Fable. This I give you aſſurance of, and likewiſe that I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Beleeve you ſuffer leſſe paine, than you have taken to deſcribe, that which you ſay my Abſence produceth in you. My beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I am ſure, cannot cauſe either affliction or ſorrow in any Man. So that if you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue your Complaints, I ſhall bee forced to begin my Reproaches; Ceaſe then your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Sorrows, and Griefs, and Sighes, and Lamentations, 'tis a Language that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſts
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15760:75"/>
mee extreamly, and which makes mee ſpeak thus freely to you, in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Other more obliging Anſwers to the Precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am ſenſible of the affliction, which my abſence cauſeth in you, but as it is unavoidable in the Condition I am in, you muſt of neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to be patient, ſince it is the only Remedy of your Ill. Doe not undertake a Journey to ſee me, but expect ſome occaſion or other, which will ſoone offer it ſelfe. Comfort your thoughts with this hope, and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will partake in the Sweetneſſe of it. What need you feare? know you not, that if you love me extreamly, I will revenge my ſelf with the ſame weapon? and if you be conſtant I wil looſe my life rather than my Reſolution to dye</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt faithfull ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:15760:75"/>
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF I had the power to comfort you with my Preſence, you ſhould ſoone ſee mee where my Letter is now. But being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Subjection of a Father and Mother, who give mee not ſo much as the Liberty to write to you, all that I can doe is to ſteale it, to comfort you with the Hopes of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. Beleeve mee Sir, I wiſh for it with Paſſion, ſince I am to that Point</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters proteſting Love and Fidelity.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am conſtrain'd to tell you, that of all the Perſons in the World you are ſhe only whom I affect moſt entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Theſe are no Diſcourſes of Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, my Soule expreſſing all her thoughts with the ſame Innocence that my Mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them, having no other object but your deſert only. If you make doubt of this truth,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15760:76"/>
ſerve your ſelfe of that abſolute power which you have acquired over mee, to oblige my Endeavours to all manner of proofes. My Honour, and Life, are both at your diſpoſure; I will hazard the one and other, when you pleaſe, either for your Service, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment; ſince it intereſſeth my Quiet, that I be eternally</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obedient, and moſt faithfull ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THough I ſhould ſay that you are the only object of my Reſpect, and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, I ſhould repreſent but one part of the Eſteeme which I make of your deſert: for I find you raigning ſo abſolutely in my Soule, that I have no liberty left mee, but only to publiſh in al places where I come, that I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble, moſt obedient and moſt faithfull ſervant, and ſubject, <hi>M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:15760:76"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lovers of this Age, are ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to divulge their Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Affection in all places, that they are as far from perſwading the beleefe of it to others, as they are from the true feeling themſelves. What paines you take in ſeeking to give me aſſurance that you love me! I am ſo farre from giving credit to the leaſt ſyllable of thoſe diſcourſes made to my Advantage, that it is a great trouble to mee to heare them, being fully ſatisfied if you love mee in that height that I honour you, ſince I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu are too eloquent to be Amorus; a Paſſion ſo extreame as that which you feigne in my behalfe, could never bee
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15760:77"/>
able to expreſſe it ſelf, but in feeble tearmes. Which forces me to a beleife that you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed more time in Compoſing that pretty Letter, than ever you did in the Sufferings of Love. But howſoever, your deceit is not ſo unpleaſing to me that I ceaſe to be obliged to your care in turning it to my Advantage, which I ſhall alwayes receive, when you are pleaſed to reckon me in the Number</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervants.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters Complaining of a Neglect.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am Conſtrained to ſay that I am moſt unfortunate, ſince three years ſervice could never obtaine of you to grant they were pleaſing or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Truly, though that recompence (as proceeding from you) be of an infinite value; yet me thinks the effects of ſo many dutifull regards, might have merited ſome ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of your Civility. But ſince I have already learned my leſſon of Love, I
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:15760:77"/>
am ſufficiently inſtructed in ſuffering: fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my thoughts with the Comfort of this Conſideration, that 'tis You are my Miſtreſſe, and I</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another upon the Same.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Should never have conceived, that ſince you are publickly honoured by all the World, and perfectly by mee, you would have recompenced my Reſpects with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and my Love with Hatred. 'Tis true, the Slavery wherein I am tied, forbids me to demand a reaſon for what you doe. Yet my Priſon allowes me this Liberty, to tell you that you are too rigorous to be ſo beautifull: and that except you change this ſevere Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, wherewith you tyrannize over mee, you will run the hazard to loſe</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>The moſt humble, and moſt obedient of all your ſervants.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:15760:78"/>
               <head>Anſwers to the Precedent Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wonder you ſhould Complaine of my Neglect, having alwayes had E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme for your Deſert. 'Tis true, my auſtere Humour has oftentimes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you ſubject to greive; but, I beſeech you think I was never guilty, but in appearance only, of that which you accuſe me, being alwayes inclined to nouriſh a good opinion of your Merit, in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Anſwer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu have no pretence to divulge mee the moſt cruell and diſdainfull Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man alive: for when you maintaine
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:15760:78"/>
ſuch diſcourſes, thoſe that know my diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will eaſily know you are in Anger; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe neither could they excuſe your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, nor I your misbeleife. If my actions had merited the proofe of your Study, you would have had a better opinion of my incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſince the firſt time that I have had the Honour to practice you; but ſuch is my misfortune, that all my Endeavours are not able to nouriſh in you a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters Complaining of Inconſtancy.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Never thought that after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proteſtations of Fidelity, you would have loſt even the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of having made them. Hereafter, Frailty ſhal not be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd an adjunct of Humanity, ſince in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15760:79"/>
yours you are moſt inhumane, having there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by expoſed to the utmoſt perill one of your moſt faithfull Admirers. But live conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in your new Conqueſt, and know that of all the Servants whom your Fickleneſſe ſhall acquire you, you will never find any that will equall my Affection, or be to that point that I have been</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Muſt let you know that your Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy has provoked in mee more Pitty, then it has procured me ill, being willing to loſe the Poſſeſſion of that to day, which I could not maintaine till to morrow. I ſay Pitty, becauſe I have ſome reſpect to your Honour, which is more intereſſed in that Action than my Contentment. I pray God this Lightneſſe may give you as much Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as it cauſed you blame, in the Eye
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15760:79"/>
of the World. I ſhall alwayes be glad of any good Fortune that ſhall happen you, as making profeſſion to be ſtill</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Anſwers to theſe kind of Letters.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall receive Praiſe rather than Reproach, from all that know the Reaſon of my Change; for I was obliged to it in ſo many reſpects, that the leaſt of them, will ſufficiently accuſe you, for having condemned mee. I will give you an account of this Action when you pleaſe, and when you are truly informed how things paſſed, I will have no other Judge but your ſelf, what intereſt, ſoever you pretend to have in the Suit. 'Tis from the Part</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:15760:80"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you knew with what violence I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to this Mutation, I make no doubt but you would eſteeme me far more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Praiſe, than Reproach. Imagine the power of a Tyrannicall Father towards his Daughter under his obedience: Shee may weep her fill, he bathes himſelfe with joy in her teares; her Sorrowes, and Lamentations doe but increaſe his fury. This is the caſe I am in at this preſent. I leave to your ſelfe to Conſider what I am able to doe againſt ſo ſtrong an Enemy. The only conſideration which remaines to mee, is, that if I have loſt the Quality of your Miſtreſſe, yet I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve everlaſtingly</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>That of <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:15760:80"/>
               <head>A Letter to demand the Picture of ones Miſtreſſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope you will grant mee this humble intreaty, which is, to give me your Picture, knowing I value the Originall more than all other things in the World; That beautifull Subſtance, whoſe Features, and Graces you animate with ſo much ſweetneſſe, appeared in my ſight ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorable, that I long extreamly after the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. You may give Comfort to this impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of mine when you pleaſe, by granting mee the expectation of that favour: Which I will place in the Rank of the greateſt Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities which ever can happen me, ſince it gives mee the nobleſt meanes of Teſtifying the Reſentment which I have, in Quality</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>of <hi>Your moſt obedient ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:15760:81"/>
               <head>An Anſwer to this Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our intreaty is ſo obliging, that I am forced to grant it, being glad you ſhould have often before your Eyes the Image of her that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours you extreamly. You will doe mee a favour to beleeve it, and likewiſe that I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter to demand a Miſtres her Haire.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope you will not wonder, if having enjoyed ſo ſweet a Servitude, I ſeek after new chaines, by demanding a Bracelet of your Haire. To tell you how highly I ſhall eſteem this favour, I muſt have recourſe either to your Merit, or my owne Love for expreſſion, and being you have perfect knowledge of them both, I leave the Conſideration to your ſelfe, together with
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15760:81"/>
that of the Paſſion which I have to your Service, as being more than Ever</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Favourable Anſwer to this Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Merit is of ſo powerfull a perſwaſion that I am forced to grant you your requeſt: I will not oblige you to ſilence, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that your Diſcretion has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready prevented my Deſires. 'Tis ſufficient to put you in mind, that as theſe favours are not Vulgar, ſo they require a ſecrecy of Faith in the Receivers. I hope you will keep it Inviolably, while you Remember that I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
